Nikolaos Mastrantonas, Ph.D., M.Eng., M.Sc.

Telephone: +30 6942940902 | Email: nikos.mastrantonas@gmail.com

PERSONAL STATEMENT

Hydrometeorologist – Civil Engineer with extensive experience in analysing and visualizing climate data & extreme conditions. My professional interest is to contribute to mitigating the negative consequences of climate change & natural hazards, with increased dissemination activities, a focus on early warning systems, and advocation for enhanced stakeholder participation.

Key Skills/Characteristics:

- Strong analytical skills, multidisciplinary background, quick learner; experienced in statistical analysis & specialized software.
- Result-oriented, passion for applied research and client satisfaction; drive for implementation within budget and timeline.
- Experienced in organizing and managing projects and coordinating teams in multicultural environments.
- Stakeholder engagement and interpersonal skills; friendly team player with a positive attitude.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

04/2023 – present Hydrometeorologist – Previsico (UK)

- Project: Flood libraries; ensemble forecasting
- Tasks: Sourcing & processing weather datasets; forecasts' evaluation; data exploitation
- Contributions: Operationalising forecasts' validation; incorporating ensembles & flood libraries for mediumrange forecasts; reducing computational time of the operational workflow

10/2019 - 09/2022 Early-Stage Researcher - European Center for Medium-Range Forecasts (ECMWF) (UK)

- Project: Climate Advanced Forecasting of subseasonal Extremes (CAFE)
- Tasks: Sub-seasonal forecasting; weather extremes; diagnostics; data exploitation; science communication.
- Research repository: https://github.com/ecmwf-lab/med-extreme-prec-atm-patterns
- Outreach activities: Videos (1, 2) about the project; blogposts on research/networking (1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8)

03/2018 - 08/2019 Research Associate Hydrologist - Centre for Ecology & Hydrology (CEH) (UK)

- Projects: National River Flow Archive NRFA (UK); National Hydrological Monitoring Programme NHMP (UK); Drought-related: IMPETUS (UK), ENDOWS (UK), SUNRISE (Africa, China, India), STAR (Thailand).
- Tasks: Stakeholder engagement; hydrological modelling; water supply stress testing; drought monitoring; seasonal forecasting; forecasts evaluation; trend analysis; data exploitation, validation, and visualisation.
- Contributions: Development of new visualisations with wide acceptance and increased understanding by the stakeholders; automation of routine processes; improvement of existing computational methods.

EDUCATION

10/2019 - 02/2023 Ph.D. in Atmospheric Science (summa cum laude) - TUBAF (Germany)

• Dissertation: "Use of large-scale atmospheric flow patterns to improve forecasting of extreme precipitation in the Mediterranean region for longer-range forecasts".

09/2015 - 09/2017 M.Sc. in Flood Risk Management (120 ECTS; distinction) - IHE Delft (UNESCO-IHE) (the Netherlands)

- This M.Sc. is offered by a consortium of: IHE Delft; TU Dresden; TU Catalonia; University of Ljubljana.
- Thesis: "Merging Near Real-Time Satellite Precipitation Products: A Case Study in Kinu Basin, Japan". The work was conducted at ICHARM, Japan, & IHE Delft, the Netherlands.
- Course Representative: Advocating for the students & representing them at international fora (EMA).

09/2006 – 03/2012 Diploma (M. Eng.) in Civil Engineering (300 ECTS; graduation ranking: 16th/239) – NTUA (Greece)

- Water Resources and Environmental Engineering major; Construction Management minor.
- Thesis: "Application of mathematical simulation for the control efficiency of wastewater treatment plants".
- Conducted four 2-month internships as Site/Water Engineer in Jordan, Greece, Turkey, and Egypt.

Training Courses (selected)

- 07/2022 Forecast Informed Reservoir Operations (FIRO) colloquium -SCRIPPS (USA) [competitive selection]
- 06/2021 The Science of Subseasonal to Seasonal (S2S) Predictions NCAR (online) [competitive selection]
- 12/2018 Resilience Action Planning Implementing the Sendai Framework at the Local Level UNITAR [UN]
- 10/2018 Good Practices in Stakeholder Engagement Dialogue Matters (UK)
- 08/2017 Becoming a Water Leader Summer Course IHE Delft (the Netherlands)
- 08/2014 Successful Negotiation: Essential Strategies and Skills University of Michigan (USA); online

OTHER EXPERIENCES

09/2017 - 10/2022 Disaster Risk Reduction Team Focal Point/Member - Water Youth Network (WYN) (international org.)

- Projects: Early Warning Systems Young Professionals Network; WYN members database.
- Tasks: Co-convening scientific events; acting as the link between the members & coordinators of the team.
- Contributions: Improvement of the organisation's database, and the internal & external communication.

05/2013 – 07/2015 Site Engineer – Grecotel Hotels & Resorts (Greece)

- Project: Renovation (internal, external, landscape) of a 5-star hotel in the municipality of Bodrum in Turkey.
- Tasks: Quantity surveying; Health & Safety supervision; assisting the accounting department.
- Contributions: Implemented changes for improving the functionality, and Health & Safety of the hotel; created a database for accessing all information; identified & corrected omissions in the accountings.

06/2009 – 07/2015 **Team Coordinator / Project Manager** – *IAESTE (international org.)*

- Projects: IAESTE Greece Alumni database creation; Job Fair Athens; IAESTE Athens reception team.
- Tasks: Social Media management; organization of many internal and external activities; cooperation with other NGOs; job raising; presentations; representative of IAESTE Greece in international conferences.
- Contributions: Improvement of the internal structure of IAESTE Greece; 24% increase in the success rate of our nominees; spectacularly increase of the popularity of IAESTE locally & nationally.

PUBLICATIONS (peer-reviewed; selected) [full list]

- Gupta, S.; Mastrantonas, N.; Masoller, C.; Kurths, J., Perspectives on the importance of complex systems in understanding our climate and climate change—The Nobel Prize in Physics 2021. Chaos 1 May 2022; 32 (5): 052102, https://doi.org/10.1063/5.0090222
- Mastrantonas, N.; Magnusson, L.; Pappenberger, F.; Matschullat, J., 2022. What do large-scale patterns teach us about extreme precipitation over the Mediterranean at medium- and extended-range forecasts? Q. J. R. Meteorol. Soc., 875-890, https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.4236
- Herrera-Lormendez, P.; Mastrantonas, N.; Douville, H.; Hoy, A.; Matschullat, J., 2021. Synoptic circulation changes over Central Europe from 1900 to 2100: Reanalyses and Coupled Model Intercomparison Project phase 6, International Journal of Climatology. https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.7481
- Hannaford, J.; Mastrantonas, N.; Vesuviano, G.; Turner, S., 2021. An updated national-scale assessment of trends in UK peak river flow data: how robust are observed increases in flooding? Hydrol. Res. https://doi.org/10.2166/nh.2021.156
- Mastrantonas, N.; Bhattacharya, B.; Shibuo, Y.; Rasmy, M.; Espinoza-Davalos, G.; Solomatine, D., 2019, Evaluating the benefits of merging Near Real-Time Satellite Precipitation Products: A Case Study in the Kinu Basin Region, Japan, Journal of Hydrometeorology, https://doi.org/10.1175/JHM-D-18-0190.1

CONFERENCES – WORKSHOPS (selected)

- Conferences EGU General Assembly 2021 [Co-convening session; poster (vOSPP award)]
 - Drought and Water Scarcity: addressing current and future challenges AboutDrought (UK, 2019)

- Workshops/ Water Resource Management & Supply in Central India IUKWC (India, 2019) [competitive selection]
 - Seminars Decision Making under Deep Uncertainty DMDU (UK, 2017)

AWARDS

- V. Outstanding Student and PhD candidate Presentation Award; European Geoscience Union 2021.
- 2nd place at Copernicus Barcelona Hackathon 2020.
- Graduated with distinction from the 'Flood Risk Management' MSc.
- 3 scholarships for attending the MSc: Erasmus Mundus; Onassis Foundation; A.G. Leventis Foundation.

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

Languages Greek (native) | English (excellent) | Turkish (intermediate) | German (intermediate)

Managerial skills Negotiation skills | Planning and implementation | Coordination of teams | Collection and analysis of data Computer skills LINUX | Microsoft Office | Analysis (R, Python) | GIS (ArcGIS, QGIS) | Hydrological/Hydraulic (HEC-RAS)

Affiliations AMS | EGU | Royal Meteorological Society | British Hydrological Society | Technical Chamber of Greece

Military obligations Fulfilled (09/2012 – 05/2013), ELDYK (Cyprus): Managing service plans and leave for up to 60 soldiers

Driving licence European Union (Greek): Category B

Others Blood Donor, First Aider

Interests humanitarian/environmental issues | history | geopolitics | swimming | basketball | travelling

Curriculum Vitae - Nikolaos Mastrantonas - email: nikos.mastrantonas@gmail.com - telephone: +30 6942940902